<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>quickviz on Thinking Through the Party</title><link>https://blog.ebemunk.com/tags/quickviz/</link><description>Recent content in quickviz on Thinking Through the Party</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.ebemunk.com/tags/quickviz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2022 Chess Candidates Tournament Recap</title><link>https://blog.ebemunk.com/candidates-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.ebemunk.com/candidates-2022/</guid><description>I wanted to do a quick recap of the 2022 Chess Candidates Tournament that saw Ian Nepomniachtchi emerge as the challenger for the second time. There were some good findings in there!
Click on the graphic to see it in full size.
.viz { margin: 1rem auto; display: block; } img { width: 100%; }</description></item><item><title>ca·coph·o·ny - a harsh discordant mixture of sounds.</title><link>https://blog.ebemunk.com/cacophony/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.ebemunk.com/cacophony/</guid><description>I always get glimpses of cool ideas when I see great data, and after watching parts of the First Presidential Debate of 2020 I knew I had to do something with it. The transcript over at Rev.com contains incredibly detailed and millisecond timestamped data.
Hearing about how chaotic the debate went (and witnessing it after digging into the data), I wanted to look at how often people spoke over each other.</description></item><item><title>Color in Books</title><link>https://blog.ebemunk.com/color-in-books/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.ebemunk.com/color-in-books/</guid><description>Project Gutenberg is an amazing source of books that are in the public domain. An avid reader myself, I wanted to make a creative visualization using the text of the great books when I came across the &amp;ldquo;Best Books Ever&amp;rdquo; list.
Click on the graphic to see it in full size.
I hope this inspires you to read one of these classics!
Interested in prints of this graphic? I have a few copies printed on beautiful art paper.</description></item></channel></rss>